<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Narrative of the siege and surrender of Maestricht, to the most Christian King, on the 30 of June</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 27 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52653</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N225</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4377</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12246863</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12246863</idno>
            <idno type="VID">56970</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52653)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 56970)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 872:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Narrative of the siege and surrender of Maestricht, to the most Christian King, on the 30 of June</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In the Savoy, Printed by Tho. Newcomb,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Maastricht (Netherlands) --  Siege, 1673.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:56970:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:56970:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A NARRATIVE OF THE SIEGE AND SURRENDER OF Maeſtricht, TO THE MOST CHRISTIAN KING.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>On the 30 of</hi> June.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>SAVOY:</hi> Printed by <hi>Tho. Newcomb.</hi> 1673.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:56970:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:56970:2"/>
            <head>A Narrative of the Siege and Surrender of <hi>Maeſtricht,</hi> to the moſt Chriſtian King.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Is Majeſty having reſolved to begin his Campagne with the Siege of <hi>Maeſtricht,</hi> thought it neceſſary however to conceal his Intentions, as far as could be from the Enemy, and leave them onely uncertain Conjectures where he would firſt Attack them, until his arrival before <hi>Maeſtricht</hi> had unfolded the Myſtery. This was the reaſon of his Majeſties aſſembling his Troops on the <hi>Lys;</hi> his coming with his Army to the Walls of <hi>Ghent,</hi> and his conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing there ſome time; his ſending out a Body of Men to paſs the <hi>Vaert,</hi> between that place and <hi>Bruges,</hi> under the Command of the Duke <hi>de Feuillade,</hi> and afterwards ſeveral Squadrons of Horſe under the Command of Monſieur; his ſending the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs <hi>de Rochefort</hi> with 6000 Horſe towards <hi>Vilvoerden;</hi> and laſtly, of his Encamping before <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> that ſo he might diſguiſe his deſign of beſieging <hi>Maeſtricht,</hi> and give equal jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie to the Dutch and their Allies; who being thus concerned for themſelves, could not ſend the Forces, they would other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe have done, into <hi>Maeſtricht</hi> to reinforce that Garriſon.</p>
            <p>His Majeſty having thus paſſed through <hi>Flanders,</hi> the Third of this inſtant <hi>June, S. N.</hi> Commanded the Count <hi>de Lorge,</hi> one of his Lieutenant Generals, with 6000 Horſe and Diagoons to go and inveſt <hi>Maeſtricht.</hi> He parted with this Body of Men about Midnight, taking his way through <hi>Tilemont,</hi> S. <hi>Truyen,</hi> and <hi>Tongres,</hi> and arrived the Fifth, in the Evening, before <hi>Maeſtricht,</hi> where he found the Count <hi>de Montal,</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor of <hi>Charleroy</hi> and <hi>Tongres</hi> with 1500 Horſe drawn out of this latter place and <hi>Maſeyck.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:56970:3"/>
            <p>At their firſt arrival they were ſaluted from the Town with ſeveral Shot, notwithſtanding which, they gave every where the neceſſary orders; and the next day, about Six a Clock in the Morning, began to Inveſt the place on this ſide of the <hi>Meuſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Seventh arrived the Sieur <hi>du Piloy</hi> with 3500 Horſe of Monſieur <hi>Turennes</hi> Army, and the next day the Sieur <hi>de Reveillon</hi> Brigadier, with ſeveral Regiments of Foot from the ſame Army. The ſame day the Sieur <hi>de la Talèc</hi> arrived like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe with other Troops, who all together finiſhed the Inveſture of the place, on the other ſide, called <hi>wyck,</hi> and a Bridge of Boats was made over the River for the Communication of the ſeveral Quarters. In the mean time, the Count <hi>de Montal</hi> having cauſed Seven thouſand Bores to come out of the Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borhood of <hi>Liege,</hi> began to work on the Lines of Circonval<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation and Contravllation: This let the Governor ſee we were in earneſt, who thereupon omitted no endeavors for the defence of the place, being very glad that he had ſome days before re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived into the Town 1000 Spaniſh Foot and 500 Horſe: Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly he cauſed all the Inhabitants, as well as Soldiers, to work for the raiſing of Three Batteries on Three <hi>Cavaliers,</hi> from whence they could ſee all our Quarters and incommode them very much; and beſides, cauſed frequent Sallies to be made through by-ways, and undiſcernable by us, by reaſon of the Redoubts which were far advanced, and the very high Corn that was round the place.</p>
            <p>The firſt Sally, they made out of the <hi>Tongres Gate</hi> with 150 Horſe, who with great courage fell upon one of our Out-Guards, which were but 20 of the Kings Muskettiers com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by the Sieur <hi>de Paygnace,</hi> the Enemy making ſlight ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of this ſmall number, whom they thought to deſtroy with eaſe, put not themſelves into that poſture they would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps otherwiſe have done, and ſo were deceived by the great courage of our Men, who made ſo brave a reſiſtance, that they killed 20 of the Aſſailants, and beat the reſt as far as their Counterſcarp, notwithſtanding they fired violently with their ſmall Shot from thence. The Sieur <hi>de Paygnace</hi> was killed with a Cannon Bullet, with one Muskettier more, and two wounded.</p>
            <p>The Ninth the Enemy made an other Salley by the favour of their Redoubts, and the high Corn, they killed two of our Men, and forced our Out-Guard to retire; but the Count <hi>d' Auvergne</hi> having notice thereof, went immediately out with
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:56970:3"/>a Party, and forced the Enemy back; Their intention was to have taken the Standards, which ſtood along the Line, and three of their Officers had already Seized Two Standards of the Kings Regiment, though they held them not long, for one of theſe Officers was killed with a Musket Bullet, and the other two taken Priſoners.</p>
            <p>During theſe firſt days of the Siege, there were ſeveral other Skirmiſhes, in which the En<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>my had no farther Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage; They loſt the Marquis <hi>de Vervic,</hi> Nephew to the Count of <hi>Rrouay,</hi> who was very much wounded, and taken Priſoner.</p>
            <p>The Tenth the King who parted at Midnight from <hi>St. Truy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en,</hi> ſeven great Leagues from <hi>Maeſtricht,</hi> arrived in the Camp about noon, accompanyed by Monſieur, with his <hi>Gens d Armes,</hi> and part of the Infantry, notwithſtanding the difficulty of the Ways, and the ſlow march of the Foot; his Majeſty was no ſooner arrived, but went to viſit the ſeveral Poſts, to obſerve the Scituation of the Place, and its Fortifications, and to aſſign the Troops that came with him, their ſeveral ſtations. On this occaſion there happened a new Skirmiſh, in which the Kings Dragoons took one Priſoner, whom his Majeſty imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately gave his Liberty again, with this Commiſſion, that he ſhould tell the Beſieged, That unleſs they Surrendred ſuddainly, they could not expect any Quarter.</p>
            <p>The following night his Majeſty was at the By-watch, as he hath been ever ſince; The next Morning he cauſed the Bridge of Communication to be finiſhed, and the reſt of the Infantry being come up, he aſſigned them their ſeveral Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters round the place. That day Monſieur went and took his Quarter on the ſide of <hi>Wyck,</hi> with 6000 Horſe, and 9000 Foot; The King took his at a Village called <hi>oilre,</hi> which is about half Canon ſhot from the place, and ſecured in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure from the Enemies Cannon, by a ſmall Hill that covers it.</p>
            <p>The Twelfth was imployed in working at the Lines of Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convallation and Contravallation: That night his Majeſty cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed a Redoubt of the Enemies, which was far advanced, and incommoded us very much, to be Attacked, which after a ſhort diſpute was taken, moſt of them that defended it, which were 30 in all, having been killed or taken Priſoners.</p>
            <p>The 13 happened a ſmall Skirmiſh between 50 of the Enemy, and ſome of our Guards, who at firſt, as being much the weaker, were forced to give way, but being aſſiſted by a Party ſent to them from the Camp, they beat the Enemy to the foot of their
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:56970:4"/>Counterſcarp. That night his Majeſty cauſed the Infantry to match nearer to the Place, being ſecured by the Cavalry, and Monſieur did the like on his ſide, ſo that the Beſieged could not ſtir out of their Counterſcarp, without coming under our Shot.</p>
            <p>The Fourteenth we ſeized on a cloſe way, by which the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my ſecurely made all their Salleys; 2000 Horſe were Poſted there, and a Retrenchment made to ſecure them againſt the Enemy. This day the Lines, as well on this as the other ſide the <hi>Meuſe,</hi> were finiſhed, although that of Contrevallati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is about four Miles about, and that both are 12 Foot broad, and ſix foot deep.</p>
            <p>The Fifteenth great Proviſion was made of Faggots, and other Neceſſaries for the Siege, the King in the mean time with his accuſtomed Vigilance, obſerving what Places were fitteſt to be Attacked, and taking care that all things were in the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture they ought to be, before he opened the Trenches.</p>
            <p>The Sixteenth his Majeſty reſolved that the Trenches ſhould be opened the next Morning, not far from the <hi>Tongres</hi> Gate, and in the mean time our Men began to work, for the raiſing of two Batteries on this ſide the <hi>Serre,</hi> and a third on the other ſide, on the Mount <hi>St. Peter,</hi> in Monſieur <hi>Montals</hi> Quarter, on the ſide of <hi>Lietembergh,</hi> the Guns being ſo ordered, that they could not onely diſmount thoſe of the Enemy, but alſo incommode them very much in their Out-works, which the Enemy were Fortifying all they could, the Women as well as the Men being employed at the Work; and in the mean time fired more furiouſly then they had done before.</p>
            <p>The Seventeenth about Nine at Night, the Trenches were opened in the places his Majeſty had appointed, which are on the ſide of his Quarter, by two Bataillons of French Guards, and one of Swiſſes, Commanded by the Duke <hi>de la Feuillade,</hi> Lieu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>enant General, on the Right, and by a Bataillon of <hi>Picar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi> and two of the Royal Regiment, Commanded by the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis <hi>de Vaubran</hi> on the Left, being in all 4800 Men, and aſſiſted by eight Squadrons drawn out of the Kings Guards, Genſdarmes and Light Horſe, under the Command of the Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier <hi>de Hautevilie;</hi> The Enemy all this while fired very brisk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon us, but killed onely three or four of ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Souldiers, and wounded a Lieutenant of the Royal Regiment; the night was very favourable to us, and our Men continued their Works till Morning, without any oppoſition, with ſo much vigor, that by break of day, thoſe under the Command of the Duke,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:56970:4"/>
               <hi>de Feuillade,</hi> had advanced 1000 Paces, counting the turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; and thoſe under the Command of Monſieur <hi>Vaubrun</hi> 200, and beſides made a Line of Communication between the two Trenches, which were at firſt diſtant from each other, above 800 Paces, and now there remained onely 1500 Paces to the Counterſcarp; The Enemy who had been very ſilent all night, about three a clock in the Morning began to fire very warmely with their ſmall ſhot upon our Musketeers, though without any great effect, there having not been above five or ſix killed, and ſome few wounded, and amongſt others the Marquis <hi>de Termes, Ayde Camp,</hi> and the Sieur <hi>de Villeron;</hi> likewiſe <hi>Ayde de Camp,</hi> received light hurts; Here I cannot omit to tell you, that the day before, in the taking of the Redoubt, the Sieur <hi>de Charlieu,</hi> Captain of the Kings Regiment, was ſhot in the Shoulder.</p>
            <p>The Eighteenth by break of day, our three Batteries began to play upon the Town, one having 12 Pieces of Cannon Mounted on it, the ſecond 8, and the third 6, each of them carrying Bullets of 24 pound weight; This day 3800 ſhot were made into the Town, not without doing conſiderable executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, In the Morning we Battered down two of the three Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valiers, which they had raiſed upon their Rampart, and by four in the afternoon we had likewiſe Battered down the other; However the Enemy with much difficulty Mounted two of their Guns again, with which they fired into Monſieur <hi>Montal's</hi> Quarter, though without any effect, whilſt he was acting with all imaginable vigor: About 11. a Clock this day, Monſieur <hi>Montal</hi> ſent out a Party of 50 Men, of the Regiment of <hi>Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devile,</hi> to ſeize on a Houſe, which ſtood in his Quarter, which was Guarded by 18 Souldiers, Commanded by a Lieutenant and a Sergeant, who had orders from the Governor not to yield, he having promiſed to ſend them on all o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>caſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns, ſuch Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cors, as the importance of that Poſt would require; Our Men ſoon made themſelves Maſters of one Place, taking the Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant and his Souldiers Priſoners, with the loſs on our ſide of three Men killed, beſides five or ſix, with two Sergeants woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, as was likewiſe the Sieur <hi>de Covrelle,</hi> Major of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment of <hi>Bandeville.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Eighteenth Night, the Marquis <hi>de Rothefort,</hi> Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant General, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elieved the Duke <hi>de la Feuillade,</hi> with a Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taillon of <hi>Navarre,</hi> another of the Crown, formerly called <hi>Artois,</hi> and a thirds of the Kings; The Chevalier <hi>de Lorraine</hi> Mureſhaq <hi>de Camp,</hi> Relieved the Marquis <hi>de Vaubrun,</hi> with
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:56970:5"/>Bataillon of <hi>Piedmont,</hi> and two of the Regiments of <hi>Dauphin,</hi> being Guarded as the day before, by eight Squadrons of Caval<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, under the Command of the Marquis <hi>de Chazeron,</hi> Briga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier of the <hi>Genſdarmes;</hi> That Night the Trenches were advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced 600 Paces, and within 900 of the Counterſcarp, the Enemy all this while firing very violently to repair their ſilence the night paſt, no withſtanding we had onely two Men killed, and 14 or 15 wounded, beſides the Sieur <hi>Permangle,</hi> Mareſhal of the Kings Guards of Light-Horſe, and the Sieur <hi>de la Boſſiere,</hi> Captain in the Kings Regiment, were both wounded with a Shot from a Musket. This Night the King, who ſtill like the meaneſt Soldier, expoſes himſelf to the greateſt danger, came to viſit the Trenches, accompanied by Monſieur, who had been likewiſe in the Trenches the Night before.</p>
            <p>The Nineteenth our Batteries began to Fire again very furiouſly upon the Town, and with that ſucceſs, that we again diſmounted all the Enemies Cannon, and battered down their works. In the Evening, the Count <hi>de Lorge,</hi> Lieutenant Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, relieved the Marqueſs <hi>de Rochefort,</hi> with a Bataillon of the <hi>Marine,</hi> and two of <hi>Anjou,</hi> and the Chevalier <hi>de Fourilles,</hi> Mareſchal <hi>de Camp,</hi> relieved the Chevalier <hi>de Lorraine,</hi> with three of the Kings Regiment; the Trenches were advanced very near to the Counterſcarp, and we began to dig, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the Enemies Mines; notwithſtanding, there fell a great deal of Rain, and the conſtant Fire of the Enemy. A Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant in the Regiment of <hi>Anjou</hi> was killed, with two Sergeants of the Kings Regiment, and the Major of the Regiment of the <hi>Marine</hi> was dangerouſly wounded, beſides 17 or 18 Soldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers which were killed and wounded. The King according to his cuſtom viſited the Trenches, being accompanied by Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur, who to that purpoſe, was come from his own quarter on the ſide of <hi>Wyoke:</hi> And whilſt every one, with a great deal of bravery, endeavored to put himſelf in the greateſt danger, the King commanded, that no Voluntiers ſhould go into the Tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches without order.</p>
            <p>The Twentieth the Duke of <hi>Monmouth,</hi> being the young<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Lieutenant General, relieved the Count <hi>de Lorge</hi> with two Bataillons of the Royal Regiment, and one of Swiſſes, and the Count <hi>de Montal</hi> Mareſchal <hi>de Camp,</hi> relieved the Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier <hi>de Lorraine,</hi> with a Battaillon of the Regiment of <hi>Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deville,</hi> and two of <hi>Alſace.</hi> This Night the Trenches were advanced to within thirty paces of the Counterſcarp, the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:56970:5"/>Enemy all the while Firing very thick from their Paliſadoes, though without doing us any conſiderable hurt.</p>
            <p>The One and twentieth the Duke <hi>de la Feuillade,</hi> and the Marqueſs <hi>de Vaubrun,</hi> mounted the Trenches the ſecond time. The Two and twentieth, the Marqueſs <hi>de Rochefort,</hi> and the Chevalier <hi>de Lorraine;</hi> the Three and twentieth the Count <hi>de Lorge,</hi> and the Chevalier <hi>de Fourilles,</hi> during which three days, they carried their Trenches to the Foot of the Counterſcarp, the Enemy making all the oppoſition they could: We loſt ſome Men, but nothing near ſo many, as might have been ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, conſidering the ſmartneſs of the Service. The Twenty fourth it was the Duke of <hi>Monmouths,</hi> and the Count <hi>de Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals</hi> turn to Mount the Trenches, which being now advanced as far as could be, their next work was to lodge themſelves upon the Counterſcarp. In order to which, four ſeveral Attacks were made, two Falſe and two Real; the Count <hi>de Lorge, le chevalier de Lorraine,</hi> and Monſieur <hi>Vaubrun</hi> commanded the Falſe Attack on the ſide of <hi>Wyck,</hi> which they did with that Succeſs, that they beat the Enemy out of their Outworks, being 400 Men; the Officer that commanded them as killed with a great many others, and about 30 of them taken priſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; and had they been prepared to go farther, they would certainly have taken <hi>Wyck;</hi> in this Action they had about 100 Men killed and wounded. At the ſame time the Duke of <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth,</hi> and the Count <hi>de Montal,</hi> (for all the Attacks were made together upon Firing of Five Pieces of Cannon from the Main Battery) fell likewiſe on, Monſieur <hi>Montals</hi> Attack be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the Left of the Duke of <hi>Monmouth,</hi> who had at this time under his command the Kings Regiment commanded by Monſieur <hi>Monbron,</hi> and the Grand Muskett ers commanded by Monſieur <hi>??d' Artognan.</hi> The Attacks were made with extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary courage and reſolution, and after a brisk diſput, our men gained the Counterſcarp, and from thence advanced farther, and Attacked the outward Half-Moon which was before the <hi>Bruſſels Gate,</hi> which they likewiſe carried, though the Enemy all this while was not idle, but gave us good ſtore of ſmall Shot, and beſides blew up three Fourneaux, though without any great effect. In the mean time the Duke of <hi>Monmouth</hi> ſtood ready, in caſe our men ſhould give ground to Sally him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in perſon to their relief, which our Succeſs prevented him in; for our men fell immediately to lodge themſelves in their new Poſts; ſeveral priſoners were brought away to the number of Fourſcore, amongſt which, a Spaniſh Lieutenant Colonel.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:56970:6"/>The loſs on our ſide was not inconſiderable, there having been in this Action above 400 men killed and wounded, and many of them Officers and Perſons of note, and amongſt others Sir <hi>Henry Jones,</hi> who that Night waited upon his Grace as a Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntier, and was unfortunately ſhot dead in the Trenches with a Bullet through the Throat, at the firſt great diſcharge of the Enemy, as the Sally was made. Our men ſtill continued their Works to make a Communication between the Trenches and the Half-Moon, whilſt the Enemy retrenched themſelves on the other end of it. In working we diſcovered a Mine, in which was Six Barrels of Powder, ready to be fired: By Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of the Clock the Line of Communication was finiſhed, when on a ſudden a Mine ſprang on the Right-hand, by which, above 50 men were killed, with a Captain, and an Enſign, which was immediately followed by a Sally from the Town, who fell upon our men with a number ſo far exceeding ours, that they were forced to give ground; whereupon the Duke immediately ſent away a party of the Grand Muskettiers to go and make good that Poſt; but the Enemy were already in poſſeſſion, and not eaſie to be diſlodged, when his Grace with an undanted courage, and a reſolution befitting the occaſion, reſolved to go himſelf in Perſon to endeavor the recovery of theſe Poſts, being onely attended by about a dozen Engliſh Voluntiers, Perſons of Quality; with this Company, his Grace too impatient to paſs by the ordinary way of the Sally Port, leaped over the Works, and through a ſtorm of Shot that fell on all ſides, marched along the Paliſadoes, and paſſed through a Sally-Port of the Enemies to come to the Half-Moon, which he ſaw the Soldiers forſaking, not being longer able to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it, till he with his preſence encouraged them to return, which they did with new vigor, and being followed by what force they could rally up in the Trenches; the Enemy was the ſecond time beaten off, though not without the loſs of ſeveral Officers and Soldiers which were wounded and ſlain in greater numbers, then at the Night Attack. Monſieur <hi>d' Artagnan,</hi> Captain of the Grand Muskettiers, was killed, as he ſtood near his Grace, with a Shot through his Reins, and Captain <hi>O Brien</hi> was Shot in the Leg. The Kings Musket<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers, who behaved themſelves with extraordinary gallantry (as indeed all in general did) were moſt killed and wounded: And now came 400 Men from the Camp to reinforce us, though we had not any farther occaſion for them; for the Duke continued abſolute Maſter of his Conqueſt, and left the quiet
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:56970:6"/>poſſeſſion of it to the Duke <hi>de la Feuillade,</hi> who came to relieve him at the uſual hour. The King was at the end of the Trenches at his Graces coming out, who received him with expreſſions of joy for his ſafe return, and all manner of ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction in his Conduct. In theſe Attacks 700 Men, together with Officers were killed and wounded.</p>
            <p>The other Attack commanded by Monſieur <hi>Montal,</hi> had not the like ſucceſs, though it was managed with all the cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and gallantry imaginable, his Men having gained the Half-Moon, were again beaten off with the loſs of 500 killed and woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
            <p>The Twenty fifth at Night, and the next day, was employed in For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying our ſelves in our new Poſts, and preparing for a new Attack, which was reſolved to be made the Tueſday following, and accordingly the Count <hi>de Lorge,</hi> and <hi>le Chevalier de Fourilles,</hi> whoſe day it was, had Orders to make two ſeveral Attacks, our Cannon having as well this day as the day before, fired very furiouſly upon the Enemy, and very much Battered their Fortifications, where the Attacks were intended to be made, though in the mean time the Governor omitted no endeavors to repaie them again, and to put all things into the beſt poſture of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence he could; The Count <hi>de Lorge</hi> had Orders to Attack a Horn. work, which was on the left hand of the Half-Moon, taken the 24 and 25 inſtane, and the Chevalier <hi>de Fourielles,</hi> to attempt a Green Half-Moon on the Right hand of the <hi>Bruſſels</hi> Gate, near that part which is ſet under Water. About eleven of the Clock at Night, the Sign being given by two pieces of Cannon, a Mine of ours which was fixed under the Horn-work, was Sprung, and immediately thereupon, our Men made the Attack; The Enemy made a ſtout reſidance, firing very fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly upon us from all parts, caſting abundance of Granadoes amongſt us, and beſides Springing ſeven Mines, one after another; notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding which, we beat the Enemy, and gained the Poſt, having killed many of them, and taken ſeveral Priſoners, amongſt which was, the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor of the <hi>Italian</hi> Regiment, and ſeveral Miners, who diſcovered ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral other Mines, and which were by that means prevented from Spring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; In the mean time <hi>le Chevalier de Foureille,</hi> advanced as ſuccesſully on the other ſide, who after a hot diſpute, made himſelf Maſter of the Green Half-Moon, and thence advanced farther, and gained all their Out-Works; Some of the Priſoners ſaid, that the Governor himſelf Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded in the Out-Works, the better to encourage his Men, and that he ran great danger of being taken Priſoner; This done, our Work was to ſecure our ſelves in our new Acquiſition, which had coſt us this day, about 400 Men.</p>
            <p>Wedneſday Night the Duke of <hi>Monmouth</hi> Relieved the Count <hi>de Lorge,</hi> and Monſieur <hi>Montal</hi> the Chevalier <hi>de Foureille,</hi> who advanced ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what farther, till within 10 or 15 Yards of the Ditch, which was dry, there being nothing between us and the Town, but this Ditch, and the Walls, which were very much Battered; In the mean time the Enemy
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:56970:7"/>omitted nothing on their part, to defend themſelves; that night they Sprung five Mines very near us, yet not ſo near, as to do any execution, which we thought they would have followed with a Salley, but they did not; The Thurſday which was the 29, the Duke <hi>de Feuillade,</hi> and Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>Vaubrun</hi> came upon the Guard, but nothing paſt that night; on our ſide we were preparing for a general Aſſault on the Town, and the Beſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged began it ſeems to think on a Surrender, looking upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be unable, after the loſs of all their Out-Works, and having no hopes of Relief, to hold out, accordingly on Friday Morning early they deſired a Parley, and in two hours time the conditions for Surrender were agreed, and immediately the Kings Regiment of Guards marched in, and took poſſeſſion of the <hi>Bruſſels</hi> Gate: The Articles were, That the Garriſon 5000 Foot and 1000 Horſe, ſhould March out with Bag and Baggage, Drums beating, Colours flying, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with two pieces of Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, and one Mortar piece, either to <hi>Boiſleduc</hi> or <hi>Breda,</hi> as they thought beſt. The Governor preſſed hard, to ſtay in the Town till Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, but at length agreed, to march out the next day, the 31 inſtant.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>THus we have ſeen an end of this Siege in three weeks time, to the great Surpriſe of all people, who conſider the ſtrength of the place, and the great Garriſen that was in it, and eſpecially of thoſe who thought it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pregnable, or at leaſt, that the taking of it would have caſt the King many Months, and greateſt part of his Army; Though certainly it may chiefly be attributed to the great Conduct and extraordinary Courage of the King, who hath himſelf during this Siege, performed all the parts of a General, with an unintermitted Induſtry and Vigilance, In this Siege we have had 2000 killed, and as many wounded And the Enemy has loſt 1000, the Italian Regiment that was in the Town, being quite deſtroyed; and to do them right, they defended themſelves very ſtoutly, and perhaps might have made the Siege laſt longer had they not put ſo much confidence in their Mines, on which account perhaps they uſed the leſs oppoſition, to hinder our approach at firſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:56970:7"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
